Hello this is John from cave of programming to come.
I'm actually having this video I think about two years after recording this swing course.
And there are three things that I want to tell you about in this video.
The first is the applet support in browsers is even less good than it used to be.
I think the splits are really on the way out.
So in the code that I'm about to show you are going to cover animation.
I'm going to do it in the context of an Aplin.
And that's all going to work in Eclipse.
But there's one video where I show you how to deploy it they apply applet with h.t. email.
Now the Chrome browser I believe removes support for applets basically in April of this year which is
now 2015.
So you won't be able to get up to work on Chrome and it won't work on opera.
It should work on other browsers.
Although you may have to fiddle around with your security settings to get it to work.
And the only place where I've really ever seen applets used seriously is has been in in-house software
where people can control centrally the browsers that people are using and the security settings as well.
So the bottom line is this tutorial is still good it's still good for learning about animation especially
But when we come to that video on deploying applets he might want to consider skipping that.
Unless you envisage you might be developing an in-house applet some some day you know for use within
a company and then it's still hopefully relevant.
So what I'll do is just to kind of remedy that habit is at the end of this section.
I'll add a video.
It shows you how to turn this code into a desktop swing application and that's also quite a good thing
that you could have a go yourself if you want a little bit of a challenge which you should be able to
do.
If you follow this course so far so that the code that were going to see is going to work in Eclipse.
It's only that one video on deploying the apla that is potentially going to be tricky and if you're
using Chrome or opera it just won't work now unfortunately anymore.
So the other couple of things that I want to mention is that I have got a Mac computer now and when
I tried to run this coupler in the Mac.
So if I do this this is what it should look like so we should end up with this at the end of the course
and it's a ball bouncing off a bat.
But in fact let's just go back.
I found that it actually initially crashed.
So there's this game Java where were going to develop a sort of component that shows this bouncing ball
bouncing around sort of custom components.
And this has got in it some code for hiding the cursor and the way we do that is we create a blank image
and set that to be the cursor using this hidden cursor equals get toolkit create custom cursor thing.
Now the problem is that when you create a cursor you have to specify a hot spot and that's the spot
within the cursor image that actually clicks on things and originally in the code that you're going
to see in the following section.
I set that spot to be 1 1 and if you do that I discovered on a Mac it doesn't actually work.
Let's try that again.
Go to runouts what happens is it.
This is sort of blank the applet viewer from Eclipse and we get this sort of traceback an exception.
And if you look for the first line in here it's actually in code that that we've written that were going
to write in the following section.
It's right here on this line it creates the custom cursor and that can be fixed by setting the hotspot
to point zero zero.
Then it works.
So in theory swing ups are completely cross platform but it's true that sometimes they're not as crass
a cross platform as you'd like.
And if you really want to deploy swing application of any kind it is good practice to test it on all
the platforms all the different versions of operating systems that you might want to deploy it on which
unfortunately I can't do.
I used to have windows and I've got just Mac but this is the only thing I've discovered that really
doesn't work at least on this version of the Mac operating system.
So let's let's run that again now.
And now it's fine.
The other just little minor point is when I developed this program as you are going to see in the following
section.
We've got this bit where we've got like a bat that we use to bounce a ball around.
And originally when we detect an intersection of the ball with the bat I reverse the x and y direction
and the ball.
But that gives a very unnatural bounce because it means that the ball.
Bounces off at the same angle that it hit the baton like this which is which is a bit strange.
I don't know why I did that originally Really.
So to fix that if you don't improve that habit just comment out the pit of code that you're going to
see soon which reverses the x direction of the ball.
Only reverse the y direction when it hits the bat.
So that's that's it basically.
And so my suggestion is that you work through this code.
Get the applet running any clips you might want to skip the section on deploying applets because you
might you might see an applet if you're running in-house software within a company.
But other than that to be honest they're not really that much use.
And they've always been a bit rubbish.
You know they used to lock up your browser and stuff.
If you do want to deploy a job application on the Internet you can do it with Java Web start and then
it doesn't run within the browser or at least the way that works in all browsers won't run within the
browser on Chrome.
For example you have to download a little farm and click on it and that starts a job program on your
desktop.
That's kind of outside the scope of this tutorial.
It's a little bit involved.
You have to do some command line stuff a little bit to sign your jaw and to deploy it on the Internet.
You'd also have to pay for a certificate from a certificate authority so are not going to go into that
but if you did want to deployer Java out from the Internet that would probably be the best way to do
it.
And it's called Java Web start.
Okay so I'll leave it there for now and I'm going to add a extra video as well at the end of this section
on how to turn your apla into a Swingle that runs on the desktop.
Okay so until next time.
Happy coding.