Hello this is John from
caveofprogamming.com.
In this tutorial, we're gonna change tack
completely, because there's
a few little things left that I still
wanna show you.
And I'm gonna show you how to put together
an applet here,
and we're gonna use lots of context for
the last few things.
But most of the stuff I show you here,
applies to any
swing application and you can use it in
any kinda swing application.
And equally the stuff I've showed you
before,
can nearly all be used in applets as well.
So applets are they are kind of
applications
that you can embed in a web page.
And often people choose to use Flash
rather than Java for
that these days, but it's used useful,
[LAUGH] I almost said useless.
But it's a useful thing to know in case
you need to know it.
And they are still used and they are still
useful.
But a disadvantage of a applet over Flash
is that if
you have an applet embedded in a web page
you'll see
an error, well not error but a warning at
the top
of your browser that says do you want to
run this applet.
And it's kinda just annoying to have to,
you
know, to have to show that error to users.
So if, I think for that reason, more than
any
other, applets aren't massively popular,
but they could be useful.
So let's right click the project folder
here, and I'm
gonna go to a New, we're gonna create a
new class.
And I'll just call this Main, and click
Finish.
Now, I'm gonna make main extend.
Extend JApplet.
So applets don't have to be Swing based,
but they can be.
And this one is going to be, cuz this is a
Swing tutorial series.
I'm gonna do Ctrl+Shift over to add the
import.
and, and click Save.
Now JApplet has a bunch of methods that
you will want
to override, or at least you'll want to
override some of them.
And let's have a look at some of the most
important ones in this tutorial.
So I've right-clicked there and I go to
Source > Override Implement Methods.
Please excuse the sound of the workmen
working across the road here.
And I'm gonna go, let's, there's a lot of
messages here, a lot of methods here, that
you could over ride, but there's about
four that are particularly important.
I think the swing specific ones, are
generally you can probably usually leave
them alone.
If you go into Applet here, its JApplet
derives or extends applet.
We've got a we've got an init method.
Init is where you do any initialization
that you have to in your applet.
So it's kind of like a constructor, but
rather than doing
initialization in a constructor, for an
applet, you do it in init.
And, and that's called when the applet's
kinda sat up.
And you would connect to a database in
init, as well if you want to.
And if you have to destroy anything, like
you have to
close the database connection or anything,
you do it and destroy.
And there's also a start method.
Start is called whenever your upload is
displayed and if the user
goes to different internet page, browses
away from the upload, stop will be called.
So if your applet has to run, in any
sense, you, like for example if you've got
a timer or a game loop, you wanna start it
running in start, and you wanna stop it.
Whenever stop is called and then it starts
cold again you wanna restart it.
So, we're gonna just work with these four,
I think and this tutorials.
so, let's just for, for a moment.
Let's just put some sysout in there and
we'll
look into this and get more detail in
future.
So sysout there we go.
All right init, lets just copy that.
And let's put destroy, destroy.
And in here I'll have start and in here of
course stop.
Now, we're gonna to look up how to embed
this in a webpage, but,
for the moment, to test your applet, you
can just click run like this.
And this is your applet running.
There is nothing to see at the moment.
You can see that init has been called.
It was called first of all, and then start
is called, and
then, if I quit this applet, we're gonna
get stop and then destroy.
And stop, bear in mind that start and stop
can be
called multiple times by the applets in
business, so to speak.
So that's it for this tutorial; join me
again next time and until next time, happy
coding.
[NOISE]