Hello in this tutorial we're gonna look at
creating Swing
components that are completely drawn from
scratch so to speak.
And I'm just going to show you the basic
principle here,
we're just gonna create a very, very
simple completely black component.
And we'll kinda enlarge on the a little
bit in future tutorials by exploring the
graphics API.
So I'm gonna show this within the context
of this applet
that I've got, and at the moment, if I run
it.
There's basically nothing in it, so it
appears
gray and it's got this texting applet up
there.
Actually I'm not sure if that a part of
the applet or, or not.
But what I'm do is I'm gonna right click
here and go to New > Class.
And I'm gonna create a component here
which I'm gonna
call Game, which is gonna be not really a
game.
But it could be the basis of a game, if
you're interested in creating games, and a
bit finished there.
Now I'm gonna make Game, extend
JComponent.
JComponent is the base class for Swing
components.
So if you've got a component that looks
like
no other component, then you probably want
to extend JComponent.
If you wanted a component that had a
panel, I'm sorry
that had a border, you probably wanna
extend JPanel for example.
And if you wanted a component to look like
a button.
You probably want to extend JButtons and
so on.
But here I'm just, use the most basic
form.
And, I can already add this game component
to my, my applet.
So let's, let's just do that.
I'll go to init here.
And in init, I'm going to say set,
setLayout, setLayout.
So, this is the same is if we were using a
JFrame of course.
I just happen to be using a JApplet here.
So setLayout, and I'm just going to, I
just want
to add one component to the, to the the
applet frame.
So I'm just gonna use BorderLayout,
because that will
enable me to just add the component at the
center.
So, and then I'll say add, do Ctrl + Shift
+ O to add the import.
Add and I'll say add new game.
And let's just add game at the center
there, so BorderLayout.CENTER.
There we go.
So now if I run this it's still not gonna
look like
anything is just grey, this is just a
JComponent that we're seeing.
But, I'm gonna go to gain now, and in this
tutorial we're
just gonna make it say Component Black to
use as a background.
But we, we'll see in a little bit about
drawing in the process.
So if you right click here, and go to
Source > Override > Implement methods.
And, JComponents has a bunch of methods,
which are,
some of which may be useful.
But, where are we?
So yeah.
yeah, so the ones I wanna override one of
these paint methods.
And the way this works is to, to actually
paint
a component, to actually draw it in other
words, paint.
Gets called by, by Swing, by the system.
And if you want to force paint to be
called, you
don't call it directly yourself, you call
a method called repaint.
And that triggers paint to be called, at
the earliest opportunity.
Cuz usually it's only called when you're,
component is first displayed.
Or when it's re-displayed after being
covered by another window or something.
Now paint actually calls three other
methods.
It calls these protective responses yellow
diamond.
It calls first paint component, the paint,
paints kinda the background of the
component.
Then it calls paintBorder, I think which
paints
the border of the component if there is
one.
And that obviously has to be on top of the
background of the component.
And finally it calls paintChildren, and
that paints any children
that you've added to the component like
buttons or whatever.
So for the purposes of this tutorials I'm
gonna override paintComponent.
Cuz I just want to create a completely
different background for the component.
And if later on I decided to add a
border or something, then I'd want to
paint that afterwards.
So, I'm gonna override this
paintComponent.
Okay and now you'll notice that graphics
object G is passed in and that is what
allows you to draw stuff basically.
But there's a little quirk here, because
this graphics G, is kind
of a graded in the history of Swing to a
different kinda object.
Called Graphic 2D, which is a child class
of graphics.
So, this G is actually pointing, it's
actually referencing Graphics 2D object.
And Graphics 2D have more capability than
just graphics.
So the first thing to do is to say
graphics, graphics
2D g2 equals and I'm going to cast the G
to a graphics 2D.
And that will get us a graphics object
with extended capabilities.
And, what will it do wrong here?
So graphics2D that should be right.
Do Ctrl + Shift + O type input.
Oh yeah, just gotta save it now.
And, and oh, I mistyped the X.
Okay save that, there we go.
And now I'm gonna set first of all the
color to use for drawing.
And then, I'm going to create a filled
rectangle
at the right size to fill the whole
component.
So I'm just going to say set color, and
call this method of JComponent.
I'm sorry of the graphics 2d, I'll say
g2.set color.
And in here.
By the way, I should mention it.
And the release methods like set clip, but
you wanna
be careful about changing the actual
graphics object that's passed in.
Because it's kinda reused in other places.
And if you wanna do really radical crazy
things with your graphics object, like
doing set clip.
You probably wanna create a new, you want
to clone this graphics object.
Create a new one and manipulate that.
But here we're not gonna do anything too
crazy.
So I'm gonna call set color.
And I'm gonna pass in there color.black.
And you notice you get like lower case and
upper
case versus these constants, but you can
use either one.
It doesn't matter.
So color.black is just a static, static
member of the color class.
And then I'm gonna say g2.
And you've got methods like draw.
Draw, which you can pass a shape into.
We'll cover that later.
If I want to use a fill method such to
fill an area.
And here, I'm going to use, actually, for
this
tutorial, it's easier just to use
fillRect, I think.
So, if I say here fillRect and pass in 0.
And 0 get width such as calling it a
JComponent method
and get height, getHeight and if you're
going to do.
If you're gonna literally treat this
component like
a normal component and add children to it.
You should be aware that components can be
opaque or not opaque.
And you have to kinda, if opaque is
false, that means that the background
should show through.
And you have to think about that if you're
gonna add child components.
But here, I just wanna create a black
background.
And then draw shapes on it.
So I don't have to worry too much about
the subtleties of this.
So I done g2.fillRect and that's gonna use
the color that I've set.
And now, if I run this, you can see we've
got a applet with a
black background, and now I can use that
as a base for drawing other things.
And if you wanted this, for example, to be
an
image, then, you could draw images here if
you want.
But, probably the simplest thing to do
might be to
just make this a panel instead of just a
JComponent.
And then set the icon on it and for the
icon pass the
image that you want to use and we covered
that in previous tutorials.
But you can now draw all kinds of stuff
from there and do some animation if you
want.
And we're gonna look into that.
Okay.
So that's it for this tutorial and until
next time happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]