Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
drawing shapes.
So we're gonna explore the graphics API
just a little bit.
And in the moment we've got this applet.
And I'm gonna stop by just re-sizing it up
a bit, let's go to
main here, and in, in it, I'm gonna say
here set, size.
And let's set it to maybe 600 by 500, that
should be a good size to work with.
Run that.
There we go, that's better.
Okay, so I'm going to go to, I'm at my
game component here.
And, I'm going to work with this
paintComponent method.
And I'm going to add just a couple of
shapes in here.
So, to, to add shapes, you basically need
to, well firstly, you'll want to set the
color.
So I want to say g2 dot, let's move this
out here.
So those two lines need to go together cuz
we're
setting the background color here and then
filling the background.
And then I want to say g2.setColor.
And let's have a red sphere here.
And so I'll say setColor, Color.red, red.
And I'm gonna use a method called g2.fill.
And there's also g2.draw.
And I want to draw a circle and I want my
circle in this case to be filled, all the
way through.
So I'll use Fill.
If I just wanted to draw literally a
circle, like
the edge of a circle then I would use
draw.
And now, I'm gonna tell it to draw a
shape.
So I'm gonna create a new shape here and
the type of
shape that I'm gonna use is, it's Ellipse
2D.
And it's actually an inner class of the
Ellipse 2D class.
Called double, that allows you to supply,
double precision arguments for the Ellipse
parameters.
So the, let's see, let's just add the
input there for Ellipse 2D.
And maybe we can bring up some more help
information.
So we basically go the x, y, width and
height of this Ellipse.
For x, I'm just gonna put in 100.
This is pixels, and y100.
This is pixels and the y measures from the
top of the screen down.
And, since it's say, gonna be a, a circle,
I'm gonna make.
Let's make this maybe, I don't know, 15 by
15, so 15 high and 15 wide.
And if I run this, there's my circle.
And it doesn't look very nice at all, at
the moment.
And one thing I can do
is to turn on antia, antialiasing.
And the way to do that is on your graphics
2D, say g2.setAddRendering.
Not AddRendering in, I want
setRenderingHint, that's the one.
And I need here, so rendering hint have
like keys and values.
And the key here is going to be
renderingHints.
Let's add the import there, dot, or maybe
it's renderingHint.
Yeah, there we go, RenderingHints.
And I want to turn on anti-aliasing so
I'll say KEY_ANTIALIASING here
and the values going to be
RenderingHints.value.
So you see, see this is instruction in
keys and values.
And I wanna set anti-alias on.
I don't know quite why it's got this
strange syntax.
But that's how it works.
And if, if I run that now, you can see
that it really does look like a nice
little circle there.
Let's add one more shape for this
tutorial.
Let's say g2.setColor, color Color.blue.
And I'll say g2.draw and so the, not
draw actually fill, I'm gonna use fill
again.
And draw and fill both take a shape.
And Ellipse2D.Double is a type of shape.
And there is actually a line shape that
you can use.
So line 2D, but what I'm gonna use is, and
there may well be other shapes.
I'm not sure, but usually use line ellipse
and a rectangle.
And here I'm gonna use actually rounded
rect, rounded, I think it's called rounded
rect, RoundRectangle2D.Double.
Let's just see if I can add the input
there.
Ctrl + Shift + o, and let's just call
let's just call it round rect
and don't go RoundRectangle2D, sorry
RoundRectangle2D.
So I want that, and I'm gonna say new
And I think we've got double, there we go,
we've got a double constructor again.
And so you see they, they provided
kinda double the float purchase of these
classes.
I'm not really sure, that's just how it
works.
And once again, if I hover my mouse over
there.
[INAUDIBLE] added import.
I can see we've got, an x, y, width,
height and the arc width and the arc
height.
And that, that arc width and ar, aha,
sorry, [LAUGH] the arc width and
arc height control the width and height at
the rounded bits on the end.
So let's say let's put it roughly in the
middle, like 3 maybe 200.
This going to be off to the left of it,
200 x, y, and width and height.
So the width I'm gonna make it, maybe,
maybe 300.
And the height, let's make it quite, not
very high.
Let's make it like maybe just 20.
And then, arc width I'll have that at 20
as well.
And arc height, let's set that at 20.
And let's see how that looks.
And now we've got rounded rectangle there.
Actually, I'm going to make that maybe a
bit less wide.
So let's reduce the width to 1, maybe 100
actually and the
height to maybe also 100.
I don't know, sorry that's x and y, isn't
it.
Let's leave that as it was.
It's awfully confusing.
Okay, so that's x, y, width, I want to
reduce the width possibly to 100.
And the height to ten.
Okay, that's probably what I want.
So, in future tutorials, I'm gonna show
you how to
turn this kinda into a butt, that's gonna
hit this ball.
So we're gonna have a really, really
simple game.
With no, I'm not gonna bother putting any
scoring in.
I'm sure I can leave that to you.
But a really simple game just to
demonstrate some,
further techniques, like using timers, and
double buffering and animation.
This sorta thing.
Okay, so we'll leave it there for this
tutorial.
Join me again next time.
And until then, happy coding.
[SOUND]