Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at
deploying your applet.
So applet deploying applets can get
potentially a little bit complex.
And can do stuff like figure out if the
user has the right version of the the
Java plugin needed to run it and download
it automatically if not and that kind of
thing.
But in here I'm just gonna show you a
really simple way of deploying
it and if you need more information I
shall refer you to Google because I
don't want to get too diverted with
applets cuz this is really a Swing
tutorial, but just for the sake of
completeness, let's take a quick look at
this.
So at the moment my applet runs and I've
got this applet that's set to 600 by 500
here.
And I'm gonna right click the project
folder and
I'm gonna go to Export JAR file cause I
want to create a JAR file with all my
applet's resources and class file and I'll
click Next.
I often find with this wizard actually
that it remembers settings
from previous projects, and sometimes that
can cause problems and you'll have
to fiddle around with it a bit and make
sure it
has settings compatible with your current
project which is a slight annoyance.
And but I've actually filled in some
settings already to, to check that this
works.
And, I want here to export generator
class files and resources, that's very
important.
I could put my source files in there as
well if I want but that's absolutely not
necessary.
And I'm gonna export this to this path
here.
I'm gonna call it deploy.jar.
I'm calling it deploy.jar it could be
called absolutely anything.
We're gonna export that JAR file to this,
this directory.
And let's just go through the list click
Next, and you
probably want to uncheck export class
files with compile errors because of
course there shouldn't be any compile
errors in your code if
you're exporting it and if there is you
need to fix them.
But the compile warnings you don't need to
worry
about cuz they can be stuff like not
having a
serialization ID when you know, eclipse
thinks you, should
or java thinks you should and that's
completely not important.
So I click Next here.
And I, I set these settings for a previous
project and now I can't unset them so what
I've done is just, it wants to say this
manifest file, which contains information,
meta information about the applet.
We want to save it in my project
directory, so I've set it to
the current project directory and call it
manifest.mf, but this is really not
important.
Just as long as you can bond some settings
in
there that lets your jar be created
successfully then it's fine.
And if you haven't touched this you
probably don't need to touch it.
So I don't need to set the main class for
an
applet and I'm just gonna click Finish
keep my fingers crossed.
So I got warnings which is fine, but if
you
get errors that's a problem and I'm just
gonna click OK.
And now if I go to that directory,
the one that I selected, I've got this
deployed.jar.
And now, I'm going to create and HTML file
to view that deploy.jar.
And I could probably use Eclipse, but it's
simpler to use just a plainer kind of
program
it's text, and I'm going to use the free
Notepad ++ for this, which is, I highly
recommend.
And you can just just do a Google search
for Notepad pu-,
.
Notepad++, and you'll find it.
So I'm gonna create a minimal HTML file
here a minimal webpage, and I'm
gonna have an opening HTML tag and a
closing HTML tag.
And to embed the applet in this I'm gonna
use
the applet type, which I think is actually
deprecated from HTML4.
So if you really want to seriously get
into
applets, you probably want to take a
little bit of
time to look up the official latest best
way to
deploy an applet and and to bundle that
code in.
I'm just going to use a simple applet tag
here.
And let's close the tag, there.
And I'm gonna have a few attributes here.
I'll have a, a width matching the,
matching my
the width I set in my applet in it.
Width of 600.
And I'm gonna have a height of 500.
I think these values are all not
mandatory, but I'm not sure.
And the important attributes that you do
need are, firstly
archive which has to specify the location
of your JAR file.
And we'll see in a minute, this is gonna
be a URL if you're deploying it on the
web.
But since this is going to be in my local
directory and since I'm
going to save the HTML file in the same
directory as the JAR file.
I just need the name of the JAR here,
deploy.jar.
And finally, the code attribute, again
very
important, and that's gonna specify your
main class.
And my main class here is.
It's it's this class in the default
package called main.
So you need the, the full class path
there.
So if this is a patch called, package
called gooey, I'd need gooey.main.class.
But this is in the default package, so I'm
just gonna set
that to main.class and I'm gonna save
this.
And I'll save it in the same directory as
the deploy.jar I've created and I'll just
call that applet.html.
And let's just run this by I'll just
double click it and open it in my browser.
And the only thing about applets is you
get this thing here.
Actually this is saying my Java plug-in is
out of date.
I'm just gonna click, run this time.
Say that I want to run the applet.
And there is my applet.
It doesn't do anything at the moment but
you can see that it has displayed.
Now if you let's say for example, you have
your let's create a package here.
Like I don't know.
So I'll say New>Package>gui, let's say,
Finish.
And let's take these files and move them
into the GUI package.
And, so now they're in there, and if go
look
at name, you'll see it says package GUI at
the top.
And I'm gonna right click again and go to
export and JAR file next.
I'm gonna to go through screen with the
same settings, and now
if I wanna deploy it I'm gonna have to say
GUI dot.
In fact, I think I need slash.
Well let's just check this.
So if I run that now and run this time.
Then yeah I actually need, because it's,
this literally references
the file within JAR, I think it's slash
that you need.
Okay.
So let's check that.
Run this time.
Okay.
There we go.
So you've got to make sure, because when
you when
you create packages, of course they map to
kind of folders.
You probably know already.
They kind of map to folders in your
directory structure.
So, in my JAR file I can hear, in
my bin, it's going to end up with a GUI
folder like that, with my class in it.
And that's gonna match this here.
Now let's just take a quick look at what
you do
to deploy it on the internet, and that's
very, very simple.
And I've actually got a I've actually got
a web I've got a
a server running the Apache web server is
running on my on my machine here.
And let's just go into applet here.
And actually I don't know if I can maybe
cut that from there.
Yeah, seems like it will let me.
Let's go to, I'm gonna go to a folder on
my disc called picture squirrel.
And the reason it's called picture
squirrel is.
Oh yeah, I can't actually cut it because I
think my Chrome
browser is kind of got a lock on this
file, so I'm gonna
copy it instead, I'm going to copy and I'm
gonna go to the
directory that my web server's serving
things from and paste it in there.
And just to prove the that this works,
I'll change the name of this actually.
Let's call that applet.jar.
Now, this directory, cpicturesquirrel
here, it's called picture squirrel
because I'm working on a website called
picture squirrel.
But this this map's to my local host
matches the local host on my machine.
So if I go to local host here this is the
website that I'm
running, and now what I'm gonna do is
gonna take this HTML file and applet.
Let's right click > copy in this applet
folder.
And going to paste it in this
picturesquirrel folder, paste,
and let's right click and edit in
notepad, Notepad++, because I changed the
name of it, I need to change it to applet.
Now this now needs to be a URL because the
whole point of what I'm showing you here
really is
that if you have this JAR on the internet,
then
in your HTML file, this is gonna stay the
same.
This is fine, but you're going to have to
change this to a URL.
So I'll have HTTP
colon slash slash, and of course this is
gonna have to be, in my case localhost.
Because I'm just running this on my local
machine.
Strobe applet.jar.
And of course, you'd probably want to
check that, that is correct.
Let me just copy that, and go to my
browser here, and paste it in here.
And it seems not to have found it, so
maybe I did something wrong.
So I've got my applet.jar there.
Oh yeah, I've, I actually need to put this
in my public HTML folder.
So let's copy that and copy that and do
Ctrl+X
and go to public HTML and paste this in
here.
Oh, I've already got an applet.html but
that's not important.
I'll replace them.
So here's applet.html and applet.jar.
And let's check that the JAR file is
there.
And it is cuz it's asking me if I want to
download it.
So I know that the URL in my HTML file is
right.
And now let's go to applet.html and run
this time.
And there's my applet.
So the take home message here is let's get
rid of that.
Is that let's actually open the right one
again.
Is that if you have your applet on the
internet.
So let's see, in this case it's in my
local folder.
But wherever you put it you need to make
sure that the that this URL is correct and
correctly references your JAR file, which
you'll need to upload to your web server.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
As I said, there's a lot more you can do
with
deploying applets and, and you probably
don't wanna really use this, but
I, I just wanted to show you this just so
you
can get it working and just for the sake
of completeness, really.
So that's it for this tutorial.
Join me again next time and until next
time happy programming.