Hello there.
This John from caveofprogram-,
programming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
the Swing timers.
So I'm gonna show you this within the
context of applets, an applet.
But of course it has nothing to do with
applets this is just a convenient place to
put it.
And so in my applet I've got this main
fand I've got this main main.java
and I'm gonna give this class a private
timer.
Not a J timer, but timer instance variable
and I'll just call that timer.
And I'll add the import with Ctrl+Shift+O.
And you can see there are several timers
here.
And you may want to use a java.util Timer,
but there's a specializzed
one for Swing javax.swing Timer, so that's
the one I'm going to use here.
So I'll double click that.
And in my init method, I'm gonna say timer
equals new timer.
And the first parameter here is the time
interval in milliseconds.
So let's just make this one, well maybe
500th for the moment, 500 milliseconds.
And the second argument is a action
listener.
And the action listener interface
specifies an actionPerformed method.
And this timer will call that
actionPerformed method
every time the timer the timer kind of
runs.
So every 500 milliseconds in this case.
And I'm gonna pass in as my action my
actionListener this.
In other words, the main class here.
And to make that work, I'll gonna have
to say that the main class implements
actionListener.
Although, I could of course use an
anonymous class here.
Let's just click the arrow here.
And it will say, yeah, import action
listener.
Let's do that.
And then I can go to add unimplemented
methods and it's gonna
add the actionPerformed method down here
which would call by the timer.
Let's change that to E and this, this
initial,
this value here is actually the initial
delay as
well as the time interval, but the timer
does
have methods that are actually set the two
independently.
So you got set initially delay in set
delay.
And you can say whether it repeats or not
here.
So you can have a timer that only times
like one interval if you want.
So there's a few useful a few useful
things there.
But I'm not going to use them here.
What I am going to do is this is very
important for
applets, but won't concern you if you're
not working on an applet.
For an applet, in your start method,
there, you need
to because in this case, I want this timer
to run.
I want it to do some animation in my
applet.
And applets must start in response to the
start method.
So I'm going to say timer.start here,
which actually starts the timer.
And this will be called by my applet
becomes visible in the internet page.
And I'm gonna stop my timer whenever my
stop methods called in my applet.
Cuz for applets, when your internet page
with the
applet on loses focus, stop gets caught,
and you
must make sure that your applet is not
kind
of doing stuff and using CPU when it's
stopped.
So these start and stop methods can be
called multiple times for your applets.
And you you must respect them.
You must make sure that your app is not
doing any heavy processing when it's
supposed to be stopped.
And, but if you're just interest in
timers, the point
is here that you can start them and stop
them.
And of course you have to start a timer to
actually run it in the first place.
And now that's gonna call my
actionPerformed
method once every 500 milliseconds in this
case.
And just to see it running I'm gonna do a
sysout here for the moment.
I'm gonna say timer running in here.
And now if I run this code as a
Java applet we can see that the timer is
running.
I don't know if the start method, yeah, I
think, in
eclipse I don't think I can make the start
method get called.
But that's not so important.
So that's it for this tutorial.
Pretty simple to use timers, and in fact I
should mention that nearly always
when you think you need multithreading in
Swing, you probably need a timer instead.
And if you possibly can use a timer
instead of multithreading
it's much less likely to cause your
application to be slow.
And it's just much more elegant.
So timers a really good thing to use when,
whenever you whenever you can and
whenever you need something that's, that's
kind
of happening in the background so to
speak.
So that's it for this tutorial and until
next time happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]