Hello this is John from
caveofprogamming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
the basics of animation in Swing.
So at the moment I've got this, it happens
to be an applet actually.
And it's got these two shapes on it that
are drawn by this game.java and
I've got this main kind of the equivalent
of a main method.
But for an applet and in there, I've
actually, I did
a timer which I've, I've changed to run
ever 20 milliseconds.
But we look to that, like in the last
tutorial.
And this timer is running this action four
method and I'm going to
go to my game here, and I'm going to give
my game class.
A method public void update and this
update method is going to update
the positions of the shapes on my screen
to make them move around.
Now in main, I'm just going to call here
game.update
and in fact, let's take a look at where
game actually is.
So I've got, yeah, I need to make game a
field rather than just creating it here.
So here I'll get rid of that, Ctrl+X put
in game there and at the top here let's
say private Game game and in, in it
I'm going to say and down here game equals
new Game.
So I've got my game class it is on my
drawing.
And I'm gonna call here in, in response to
the timer I'm gonna call game.update.
And of course you know, if this wasn't an
applet you might even have to put the
timer code.
And the class actually draws stuff but
it's my preference.
The main pointer here is just that we've
gotta call this update method regularly.
And now I'm gonna animate in this, in
this tutorial I'm gonna animate this
ellipse which is
actually a little, kind of like a little
ball
and I'm gonna make it bounce across the
screen.
So, let's cut this from here and
I'll call that ball and I'm gonna put
private instance variable in here.
So that's gonna be a type
Ellipse2D.double.
So I'm gonna say private Ellipse2D.double
ball equals new Ellipse2D.double.
And at the moment, I should run the same
as it did before, so there we
go but now we can update the position
of that ball, whenever this update method
runs.
So let's see, one thing that we need to
do is after it take runs we need to call
repaint because
if you update the position on the ball but
you
don't redraw the screen then absolutely
nothing is going to happen.
So it's very important to call repaint and
repaint actually
tells Swing to call paint component at the
earliest possible opportunity.
So don't call paint component yourself.
'Cuz if you do that, you could end
up slowing down or locking up your
application.
Call it repaint.
And that will trigger your, it will
trigger Swing to call paint component.
And of course, this is absolutely the same
for an applet
or any kind of swing application for
desktop application or whatever.
The stuff I'm showing you here is not
applet specific at all.
And so now lets say, lets have some code
here, in fact I'm gonna give the ball a
speed.
Lets say private int speed equals
maybe I should make it a double, private
double speed equals
10.0 and let's
also give it a a next direction and you'll
see why shortly.
So private int xDirection.
Maybe, maybe I should say xDirection ball
equals
1 and private int yDirection ball equals
1.
Now to update the position of the ball in
update here.
What I'm going to do, is I'm going to say
ball.x here.
And I'm going to say plus equals if I can
find the
plus on my keyboard, plus equals, Okay.
This equals xDirectionBall
which is 1 times
speed.
So, all I'm doing is adding on to the
xDirection here.
And this, this doesn't have anything
really to do with swing in itself.
The main point here is that I'm, I'm
literally just updating the position of
the ball.
And then calling repaint, so that the ball
will then get repainted.
The screen will get repainted and the ball
at a different position in response
to a timer that I showed you how to use in
the last tutorial.
And that's all you really need to know
about animation,
but in case you're interested in seeing
this actually work.
Work, then stick with me so let's do
Ctrl+C then paste this in and let's update
the y position as well, y, there we go y
and that's gonna be yDirection or now.
I want make sure that the ball can't go
off screen.
So I'll say if ball.x is less
than zero then ball well I'll
say xDirection ball equals 1.
So if it's less than zero, it must be
because the ball's
been moving to the left and xDirection
must be negative, speed is positive.
And so i'm going to change it back to
positive, so the ball is moving the other
way and I probably also want to say
ball.x.
In fact, yeah, I think it'll work, ball.x
equals 0,
just to make sure it can't go off the
screen here.
And I also want to detect the case where
the
ball is off the screen on the right hand
side.
So that's going to be else if ball.y is
greater than
and it's gonna be, if it's greater than,
getWidth because
getWidth is gonna be the width of my, my
game component.
Which is JComponent so I'm calling the
JComponent message here getWidth.
getWidth and I need to say negative
ball.getBounds.width because
I wanna make sure that the right hand edge
of th ball does not go off the screen and
this gives me the width of the ball that
I've set in my shape.
Up here, I think it's that one and so that
should do the trick so if so I meant to
say x here that should be x.
So if the position of the ball is so far
to the right, that the right
edge of the ball is gonna be off the
screen then I wanna say xDirectionBall
equals negative 1 to make it then move to
the, to
the left and I also probably wanna say
ball.x equals,
equals all this stuff here.
I think, I think that will be okay.
We'll check.
And now I've gotta do the same again for
the y component, so let's just copy and
paste that.
And let's change the full coordinates to
y.
Let's change the x direction to-
well, not that one.
It's so easy to get confused with this
kind of stuff.
I find, so let's change the, the
directions to y.
Got ball.y and yDirectionBall and let's
change all of
the heights, all of the widths to heights,
so this should be,
there we go this should be get height.
And this should be height and this should
height.
And I think this now looks okay and I'm
gonna run this and it's not gonna look
very
good for reasons I'll explain in the next
tutorial
but it should basically animate If I've
got this right.
Let's run it and see.
[LAUGH]
And then the ball disappeared off the
lower edge meaning that the y got too
great and I'm not
really sure why because, oh yeah, I've
got, I've got a getWidth still in there.
So if the ball.y is greater than the
height minus the height of the ball then
change the y direction to minus 0 there.
So then the ball should be travelling up
because y increases downwards.
And I
think that should be okay right?
Let's run it again.
There we go, now my ball is bouncing
nicely around my screen.
I'm just wondering actually if there's any
scope here for the ball to get stuck
because I'm saying that if the, if ball.y
is less than 0, set it to 0.
Yeah that's okay and then next time yeah
this is fine.
Okay so now I've got my ball bouncing
around.
It's not too smooth but we're gonna take a
look shortly
at double buffering which can make the
animation a bit smoother.
And in future tutorials we're also gonna
animate this, this thing here which
is gonna be like a bat which the ball will
then bounce off.
So that's it for this tutorial.
And until next time, happy coding.