Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com
and in this tutorial we're gonna look
at a technique called double buffering,
that is used to make animations smoother.
And so actually I'm gonna start just by
getting rid of these these
sysouts in here, because we don't need
them, while I think of it.
And, double buffering involves doing your
drawing to an off screen image, and
then when the drawing is all complete, you
draw that off screen image on the screen.
So one big cause of flickery, or
flickering, in animation is that
you're kind of drawing stuff while it's
being shown on the screen.
And that, that can cause flickering.
And we're gonna avoid that by drawing to
an offscreen image, and
then drawing that all at once to the
screen when it's complete.
So I've got this game class here.
And at the moment, it looks like this, in
the last
tutorial, we got this ball kind of
animating, bouncing around the screen.
And
let's just minimize that.
And I'm gonna, here in a moment, I'm
drawing everything in Paint Component.
This is like a custom component directly
to the
graphics associated with this screen,
directly to this Graphics 2D.
So I'm gonna say here.
I'm gonna give it an instance variable of
type private, buffered image.
And, and I'll call that buffer.
now, let's have the import there.
Now because that's a instance variable it
will be initialized to null, and
for reasons that you'll see in the next
tutorial, I'm actually in paint component.
And to allocate this image, so I'm gonna
say if buffer equals
null, then I'm gonna say buffer equals new
buffered
image, new buffered image, and constructor
here takes
a wet fighting image type, and I'm gonna
say, get width.
That's calling my J component get with
met, method.
Get height, because I want it to be the
same size as my component, and
the image type here, I'm gonna set to
buffered
image.type
I think the one that I need here is gonna
be type int RGB, red, green, blue.
So let's, let's try that, see how it
looks.
And save that and now, I can get a
graphics here associated with my buffered
image, and say
buffer.get, get, graphics and that will
return me a graphics 2D.
So, graphics 2D G2 equals, and I think I
need to cast that into graphics 2D, which
is, which it really is behind the scenes.
And now I won't use my G2 here anymore.
I'll delete that.
So I'll carry on drawing to G2 but now I'm
actually drawing to this image.
And finally, when I've finished drawing,
I'm gonna say
G, which is the actual graphics here in
paint component.
It's passed to paint component to paint
component with g.draw image.
And I'm going to pass in, well I don't
think
I want that one, I'm going to pass in my
buffer.
And
I think there's a better constructor that
I can use.
So, I think I just need xYWidth.
Let's use this one.
So I'm gonna draw the image out of
coordinate zero.
X is zero, Y is zero.
An imageObserver.
We don't need that.
I'm just going to set it to null.
So now when I run it it's gonna draw to
my image and then draw the image to the
screen.
And, if, if I compare this to my original
one, I
don't really know if you can see any
difference at all there.
I don't think I can.
But, in theory, using double buffering,
you are less likely to get flicker.
So it's, it's probably worth doing
especially
if your application does flicker a lot.
If it doesn't, if you run it and it looks
fine, then maybe don't bother doing this.
Anyway, so I'll leave that.
And there's one other thing some people
say helps, but I'm
not really sure about it because the
jComponent has an update method.
Let's go to source > override > implement
methods.
And in here somewhere, it's got a method
called update.
Go to the bottom here and hope it's there.
There it is.
Which accepts the graphics and, update
apparently
calls paint and passes in the graphics.
And paint calls paint component,
paintboard and paint children.
But apparently, according to what I read
on
the internet, I can't absolutely vouch for
this.
Update also does a clear of the screen,
and since we're, since we are ourselves
are
actually clearing screen, here making it
black, we
don't want to have update doing it as
well.
So it may make your animation even
smoother, just to overwrite update and
call paint directly and bypass that that
alleged clearing of the screen.
Okay.
So that's over buffering and that's it for
this tutorial and
join me again next time and until next
time, happy coding.