Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com,
and in this tutorial we're gonna look
at listening to the mouse and finding out
what the mouse is doing.
And I'm gonna make this bat move around
with the mouse.
So this is an applet, but one swing here
applies to any kind of swing application.
And I've got this custom component down
here which I called game.
But it's actually extending JComponent in
this case.
And I'm gonna give this the constructor
some public game.
Like this.
And then in the constructor, I'm going to
say at mouse.
Now, you can add a mouse motion listener.
A mouse listener or a mouse wheel
listener, and in this
tutorial well, for now I'm gonna use add
mouse motion listener.
And I'm gonna say new mouse motion
listener in there and that's an interface.
So I'm gonna have an anonymous class here
which
implements the two methods, mouse dragged
and mouse moved.
Let's get rid of stuff that we don't
really need here.
And in mouse moved I'm gonna, let's just
duce this out for the moment and
say, e.get getX to get the X position of
the mouse.
And if I run that now if I move my mouse
over
here, you can see that we're getting the
exposition of the mouse.
Now just to do something with that for the
moment I'm gonna
take this and draw in this kind of
rectangle somewhere in here.
Let's see.
So I've got this, where it's a round
rectangle.
I'm gonna take that out of there.
And I'm actually gonna do, I'll do Ctrl+X.
And I'm gonna call that, bat.
Because it's gonna be like a bat to hit
the ball with, ultimately.
And up here, I'm gonna say private.
Let's paste in that code that I just cut.
And I'm gonna say,
privaterectangle2D.double bat, equals.
So we're drawing the bat.
Let's check that that still works.
Don't know why it's so much smaller now.
And
let's run that.
There we go, okay.
So there's my bat.
And now I'm gonna say here.
When the mouse is moved, I'm going to say
bat.x equals e.getX.
So I'm going to get the X coordinate of my
mouse from the mouse event that's passed
into mou, mouse moved.
And just set the position of the bat to
it.
And since I've already got animation code
in here that's updating the screen
regularly,
which I showed you in previous tutorials,
that should move the bat around the
screen.
So, let's let's run this, and then we go,
it's following my mouse.
And, actually I, I probably don't want it
to follow the I probably want the bat to
center on the mouse, so to fix that I'm
just gonna do bat.x.
Equals bat.,
I think, I think I wanna say that the X
position of the bat is gonna equal
e.getX, negative bat.get with over 2.
And the Y position, I'm gonna subtract
bat.get height over two.
Just to put the the bat, there we go, in
the center of where the mouse is.
Now if you wanted to detect mouse clicks,
it's pretty much the same, with a little
twist.
So I am gonna say, add mouse, add mouse
listener this time.
Now, I could say here, new mouse listener,
but mouse listener has a lot of
methods, it has like five or something and
I don't wanna overwrite all of them.
So, I am gonna use a mouse adapter
and a mouse adapter class, new mouse
adapter here
implements all the methods of mouse
listener which
is a dummy kind of, dummy kind of method.
Stops [INAUDIBLE] Ctrl+Shift+O.
Now if I right, if I left-click in there
and
right-click and go to Source > Override >
Implement Methods.
These are all the methods of the
mouseAdapter class.
And I'm just going to override this one in
this case: mouseClicked.
Now this has got mouse, a mouseMove
method, but I think
I'm right in saying that if you wanted to
take mouseMoved,
you've got to, you've got to do
addMouseMotionListener, because if you
do addMouseListener, you'll get clicked
events,
but not events relating to movement.
So and in here just to do something with
it, let's just say maybe I've
got this shape called ball and I'll just
set the ball.x
equal to e.getX
and ball.y equals
e.getY, so the mouse click gets
this mouse event, and the mouse event
has the coordinates where the mouse is
clicked.
So if I run this now, so I'm dragging my
bat
around and if I click, then the ball will
go there.
It actually looks like it's bouncing off
the bat, but it's, it's not, it's just
that it's setting it to the actual bat
location when I click it.
Okay so that's it for this tutorial.
And join me again next time.
And until next time, happy coding.