Hello, this is John from
Caveartprogramming.com, and in this
tutorial, we're just gonna look at hiding
the cursor.
So sometimes you want to hide the cursor
and especially in
uploads but maybe another swing programs
to games and that kinda thing.
And to do that to make the cursor
invisible, I'm gonna go to
the construct of my component, which takes
up most of the screen here.
And so here's my constructor.
And I'm gonna say, get tool kit.
So every component has a method called
JComponent answer method call get tool
kit.
And I'm gonna say, set.
I think it set, or is it create?
Yeah, I've forgotten.
Oh yeah, create custom cursor.
So I'm gonna say, get talk and create
custom cursor.
And now that takes a bunch of arguments
here And the first argument is
well the last argument here is gonna be, I
think, it's just a name for the cursor.
I'm gonna set up to an empty string
because it doesn't really matter here.
Let's put the semicolon on the end.
This middle argument is the I think it's
the, the cursor kinda hotspot.
So we're going to pass an image in here
and we wanna say, where the center of
the cursor is in that image and I'm just
going to set that to point one comma one.
All right.
We need to pass a new point here just add
the import.
And the most important argument here is,
if I wanna hide the cursor, I need to
create an image here, but it's gonna have
to be a transparent image so I'm gonna
have to say new buffered image, and I'm
gonna pass in the size here of one pixel
by one pixel, and for the type of buffered
image, I'm gonna say, buffered image.
And I wanna pick a type that has a alpha
argument like type int
ARGB, A stays for alpha, and alpha means
that there's transparency in the image.
So if I put that in there, I'm gonna
create hopefully
a transparent image, that that we wont be
able to see.
So if I run that now.
oh, yeah.
You can still see the mouse.
And that's because, I need to set the
cursor, which I almost forgot.
The most important thing.
So we've done create custom cursor here
and that returns a cursor.
So I'm going to say cursor, hidden cursor
equals
gettoolkit.createcustom cursor passing
your transparent image,
one pixel by one pixel and then, finally,
I'll just do [INAUDIBLE]
and call it set cursor and, pass in that
hidden cursor.
I've just created this stuff and now
they're actually, [INAUDIBLE] the end.
And if I run this.
Now the cursor has gone, but it's still
there.
And I can still click it and, and all the
stuff
I can do before I move this bat around
with it.
Okay?
So that's it for this tutorial and until
next time.
Happy coding.