Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this
tutorial we're gonna look at key listeners
in Java.
So key listeners are actually somewhat
similar to mouse listeners
although a bit different at the same time
of course.
So if I go to my, I've got my J component
here.
And now you can add a key listener to a
particular
component by saying add key listener and
then passing in a
new key listener you could say like new
key listener, and
then just have an anonymous class
here that implements this keyListener
interface.
And just as we've done for
mouseMotionListener.
But the problem with that is, you'll have
problems with focus,
because to add a keyListener to your
component, it must be focusable.
So you may need to call setFocusable,
setFocusable and set that to true.
And also it must have the focus in order
to receive key events.
And that can be problematic at times and
if that's what you want to do.
If you just want a key listener that does
a particular thing in a
particular text field for example, then
you probably want to do add key listener.
But here, I'm gonna add a sort of global
key listener, that
intercepts all the key clicks that the
applications gets because it's it means
that my J component, which takes up the
whole screen in this
case, doesn't have to have the keyboard
focus which is what I want.
So I'm gonna say get default I'm gonna
say, actually, keyboard,
keyboard focus manager, keyboard focus
manager dot
and we're gonna use a static method of the
keyboard focus manager class called get
current keyboard focus manager.
And this kind of manages the keyboard
somehow.
And I'm gonna say add key event
dispatcher.
And, cause this will allow me to add a
class that can intercept my key events,
and the rest of what I'm gonna show you
now is very similar to what you'd do if
are adding, just doing add key list now on
a particular component, so I need a new
key event dispatcher here, rather than a
new key,
keyListener as would be the case without a
keyListener.
And let's just add, create an anonymous
class there, at the import.
Ctrl+Shift+O and right, and left-click
this
arrow and go to add unimplemented methods.
And we're just going to implement this
dispatchKeyEvent and keyListener has an
equivalent method.
And I'll just call it keyEvent.
That's passed in.
I'll just call it E.
Let's get rid of some of this [UNKNOWN].
And you return true here.
If you wanna say we've handled the key,
don't pass it on anywhere else.
And, otherwise, you return false.
And I'm just gonna return false always
here because I wanna
handle keys, but I don't wanna stop other
things potentially handling them.
Not that there are any other things, but
if there were I wouldn't want to stop
them.
So, and now here I'm going to say switch.
Actually I'll say int key equals e dot get
key code.
And now I wanna, in this case I wanna
detect which arrows have been clicked.
So you could just do a sysout on key here
and
press keys and see what key code comes up,
if you're curious.
I'm gonna do, like, switch key and, then
let's
say case and I'm gonna use key event
class.
And this is the same for if you do add
key listener and there there's a, for
example, a I
think it's arrow up.
I can never remember these values.
Let's just take a look.
Yeah, we got a bunch of, v case stands for
virtual key.
And the constants that you need for things
like the function keys and the arrow keys.
They're all vk this, vk that.
So we've got a vk up, for example, so
let's add vk up.
So if the key code equals vk up, let's
just put a break in there.
And just for now let's just do sysout
Ctrl+Space Return up.
Let's, now let's run that and check that
it's working.
So if I hit the up key now.
We can see that in a console it says up.
So that seems to be working.
And I'm gonna, mix my C editor here.
And that's, in the case that up is is
called.
I've got a bat shape object that's an
instance variable.
And I'm drawing the bat thing on the
screen.
And I'm updating, I'm repainting the
screen like every 20 milliseconds.
So I'm just gonna say back dot y, and if I
wanna
go up, I have to say negative equals let's
call this bat speed.
So because y increases down the screen,
and the screen redraws from the top.
And I'm just gonna add it, add in a prior
date.
Double that speed, which I'll set equal
to, I don't know, maybe 10.
10.0, there we go.
So I'm gonna move my bat in response to
the key being pressed.
Now, let's just copy these because I want
four
of them, so one, two, one, two, three,
four.
And I'm gonna have down, which is gonna
add to the position of the bat.
And I'm gonna have vk left, the left arrow
key, which is gonna subtract from X.
And vk right is gonna add to
x here, so, let's have add, and with a bit
of luck now, I'm gonna hit,
use the arrow keys to move the to move
this sort of bat thing around.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial and
join me again next time.
And until next time, happy coding.