Hello, this is John, from
caveofprogramming.com, and
in this tutorial, we're going to look
at how to find out when your component has
been resized, which is often useful.
So if I run this now, the whole screen
on my Applet is taken up by this custom
component.
And I'm actually doing some double
buffering, as I explained in previous
tutorials.
But it means that I've got an image here
that I'm drawing to, but if I resize my
component, then the image doesn't change
its size, even
though the custom component I've got has
become bigger.
So what I need to do is create a bigger
image where my component's resized.
And for that I need to intercept the
resize event.
So I'm gonna go into my custom component
code
here, which is called Gain, and it extends
J component.
And in the Constructor here, where I've
already got a bunch of stuff
listening to the mouse, and keys
among other things, I'm gonna say
addComponentListener.
Now componentListener takes a class that
implements a componentListener interface,
but a componentListener
interface has quite a lot of methods, and
I don't need most of them.
So I'm gonna use here, not a new
componentListener anonymous class, but a
new componentAdapter, adapter, which
implements kinda dummy
versions of all of the componentListener
methods.
Let's do Ctrl + Shift to override the
imports, and I'll
right-click in there and go to Source >
Override Implement Methods, and
these are all the, well actually, there's
only four of them, componentAdapter
methods, and I just want to deal with the
componentResized method here.
And I all I need to do for this tutorial
actually, is, is just set my buffer, my
image to null.
If the component is resized because I got
this code that I did in the previous
tutorial
in Paint component, that creates a new
buffered image
at the right size if the buffer is null.
So if I run this now, and I resize it, my
component that I am correctly, intercepts
to resize event and it makes my, my
buffer,
my double buffer bigger or smaller as is
necessary.
So that's it for this tutorial, join me
again next time and until next time, happy
coding.
[NOISE]