Hello, this is John from
CaveOfProgramming.com and in this
tutorial, we're
gonna look at using visual designers to
visually design your swing code.
Now you might wonder why I didn't show you
this to start with and this is kind
of high up on the list of priorities of a
lot of people who come to swing.
And but the fact is the visual designers
for java are not great.
They're not good as the visual designers
for the Windows,
largely Windows specific C Sharp and
Visual Basic for example.
And you sort of have to know almost all
the things
that I've shown you to be able to use them
effectively.
But nevertheless, they can save you time
and a lot of people do prefer to use them.
Although, all the professional java
developers
I've known, including myself, sort of
just prefer to write things by hand
because you know, you have more
control over your code, and once you know
what you're doing it,
it doesn't really save that much time to
use a visual designer, arguably.
And, anyway if you do want to there's one
very well-known
one you can use, I don't like at all
myself, called NetBeans.
And I find NetBeans slow and all the kind
of developers that I've known have kind of
argued that
they don't wanna use it because NetBeans
ties you to
NetBeans as far as I know, unless this has
changed.
You can't edit code that you've visually
designed in NetBeans, which is
a real disadvantage, snd I just don't find
it nice to work with.
But it is free, and and it does work.
So you may want to use that.
And a lot of people, I'm sure, do use it,
including, professionally no doubt.
The one that I recommend is an Eclipse
plugin called WindowBuilderPro.
So if you go to Google, and just search
for Window.
This is free, by the way.
Window builder, pro, in spite of the pro
name google
actually purchased this product, I
believe, and released it free.
It's free, it's a free Eclipse plugin, and
it's very nice, so if you search in
Google,
you'll find instructions for using it,
although last time
I checked the documentation was a little
bit sparse.
And, you'll find instructions for
installing it
as well, and the installation basically
consists
probably in going to, depending on your
version of Eclipse something like install
new software.
And then you'll have to add probably a new
plugin site here.
And then you'll just check the Window
Builder Pro check
box and go through the wizard, and it will
install it.
It takes a while, and you might think that
Eclipse is frozen while it's doing it.
But it actually seems to pretty much
always install without any instant.
So and then it's, you know, it's easy to
install and it's pretty nice to use.
But again, it is a fairly thin layer over
swing code.
So it will really help if you know Swing
programming, anyway, to use it.
Okay, so let's take a look.
At the moment I've got this applet.
And what I'm gonna do is in this tutorial,
I'm gonna
just add a really simple panel, which I'm
gonna visually design.
It's gonna be a start panel.
I'm gonna make it so that you click a
button on the start
panel and it goes into this game or
simulation or whatever you call it.
And we're also gonna look a little bit
later at,
refine, at making this bat actually work,
by the way.
But that's for a future tutorial.
So I'm gonna right click my GUI package
here, and go to new, other.
Where are we, other?
At the bottom there, and once you've
installed Window Builder, you'll have
among er, among these other options you'll
have this WindowBuilder item here.
And you can use WindowBuilder to design
interfaces using various GUI kind of
packages.
Swing is one of them.
SWT is another that's a bit similar to
Swing but
it's apparently it gives you a look and
feel that's
more similar to kind of native platforms,
and I've heard
that it's more efficient than Swing in
terms of memory.
I don't know.
So you might wanna use that.
And, if you've, don't worry if you, if
you've learned Swing, and then you wanna
use SWT.
You'll find so many of the concepts are
trans-variable.
And but I'm gonna use Swing here, because
we're, we're working with Swing.
This is a Swing series.
So you can design your application from
scratch, using Swing Designer.
You can create your application window, or
your J
Frames, or whatever, or your applet, using
this visual designer.
And, but, you can also equally well just
add particular
panels to, or features or dialogues, or
whatever, using Swing Designer.
And that's what I'm gonna do here to an
existing application.
And so I'm gonna click J panel here, hit
next and it's
got GUI pack, GUI package here because I
right-clicked that to start with.
Yeah of course the package is kind of
optional and
in the name, I'm just gonna call this
start panel.
And the Window Builder Pro the really nice
thing about it, have I said this already?
I don't think so.
Is that it allows you to switch between
your code and the visual designer, which
is fantastic.
So you can work a bit in the visual
designer and go to code, edit it
there, and switch back to visual designer
and
so on which is really a wonderful feature.
And when I click finish here, and so here
we've got a, we've got obviously,
code, but if I click the design type here,
we're going to the visual designer.
And I'm gonna start by, now if you start
just putting, you can
select components already down here and
just drag them onto here.
But if you do that, I think the
default layout manager is equivalent and
set layout null.
It's called absolute layout in this visual
designer.
And then, if you resize your panel, your
components are just gonna stay
where they are and it's not gonna look
very nice when it resizes.
So for that reason, I'm gonna set an
explicit layout.
I'm gonna right click here and go to Set
Layout.
And I'm gonna, so we've probably got
absolute layout at the moment.
But I'm gonna set GridBug layout here so
that
it will be, so that it will resize nicely.
And I'm just gonna make this a really
simple
panel, just to really, just to get you
started.
And I'm gonna [UNKNOWN] a, a label and a
button on it.
So are my components.
I'm gonna click label, and add that to the
uppermost left hand cell here and I'll
say new simulation maybe, no actually I
won't,
that what I'm gonna put on my bottom
button.
I'm gonna say Swing applet demo on this
label.
And I'm gonna add a button as well, so
I'll click that and then click on the cell
underneath here, and here I'll say, new
simulation, new simulation.
Now I don't want them bunched up in a
corner like that, and what
I'm gonna do is this took me quite a while
to find out because
at least at the time I looked, the
documentation was a bit lacking, but
if you go to, look at the borders here,
you've got these white areas.
And you can drag the edges of those, I can
make it fill up the panel here.
And I'll drag this upper most one lower
edge, down to about halfway.
And this lower one I'll drag, halfway as
well.
And I'll just click the label and if, if
you go into the properties panel here.
Properties designer, whatever it's called,
browser you can set various
properties like the background color of
your label or the font.
Let's set the font in fact.
So whatever component you've got selected,
you can see the properties of it here, and
I'm gonna click font here and just change
that to maybe, 20, there we go.
And with this panel still selected I'm
gonna, if
I look up here, I've got the constraints
of
my grid bug layout, and I've got my
properties
of those, which we covered in the previous
tutorial.
So for example, you can change grid
height, and grid width if
you want a cell that spans more than one
row, or column.
But I'm gonna actually change.
And there's, there's a way to actually.
If I, let's set the weight y to, 0.5.
And select the lower one there and go to
layout here
and hopefully here I'll also have similar
options.
Not sure where, I got sletlor I think in
the visual designer
there, and then if I browse down here,
wait y, I can set
that to 0.5 as well and with my button
selected
I'm gonna set the anchor, anchor here to
north, and
I'm gonna select the label and set the
anchor to south.
Scroll down here.
Where are we?
South.
And with the label still selected I'm also
gonna set the insets.
So let's, or actually, maybe on the
bottom, so I'll select the bottom —
I'll look for insets and these are all
cross properties of my grid back layout.
And let's just make the top here like 20,
20 pixels.
There we go.
That doesn't look too bad.
so, yeah, I could change the background if
I wanted, off the panel.
I don't whether to do that or not really.
Well, you get the idea.
And you can see your different components
here.
You can select them using this component
browser as well.
And you can test your, test your like
dialog, whatever it is,
quickly by just clicking this here and see
what it looks like.
And let's see if it resizes okay.
It doesn't.
Now I must confess I don't know how to fix
that in the
visual designer, but the beauty of this,
if I go back to source
here, you can see that it's setting
specific row heights and column heights
and I'm just going to delete those with
Ctrl+D, to delete the line.
So I want the weights.
I just don't want the widths.
And let's go to Save All and go back to
Design and click Run here.
And now if I maximize it, it resizes
nicely.
Hey presto.
And that's really the beauty of this
Window Builder
Pro and the reason why I like it so
much, is that whenever you get stuck, you
can
always go to the source and do a Google
search on how to do something in the
source
code and figure out how to do it there
rather than wrestle with the designer
which is at
times a little bit opaque, but it's not
too bad.
Okay.
So let's wire that panel in, and I'm gonna
do
that just by going to game, going to main,
actually.
I'm gonna give it a private, a private
instance variable.
This is my applet, main sort-of class,
private start panel, start panel, I'll
call it.
And in it, I'll say start panel equals,
whoops, I
get confused between the two keyboard
layouts that I have.
But okay, equals new start panel and just
for the moment, just for this tutorial, I,
I will replace game with start panel and
if I run that now, and there we go.
And this doesn't do anything, I can
maximize it and it still looks fine.
Should look fine at pretty much any size,
ehich is what I wanted.
That's good.
Okay.
Now yeah.
One last thing for this tutorial.
I'm gonna go back to this start panel here
and go to the, well, I'm in the visual
designer.
And if you click the button and, and you
right click,
you can see that you can add event time
list here.
For example, I could add an action event
handler, and there are
also all these other event handlers that
you can add, and you
could do, you could add all these of
course, manually, in the
code, but you've got the option to add
them here as well.
Now, to add the action event list, now,
there's a shortcut, because if you double
click the button like that, it will add
this anonymous class for you that
implements ActionListener.
So now, if I put a sysout in there,
Ctrl+Space and hello.
If I run that, then I click the button and
hello
comes out in the console down there, which
is, it's really nice.
Now what I want is for the start panel to
raise a
kind of event, that's gonna tell the the
main program to do stuff.
So if you feel comfortable with kind of
creating your own custom events, then you
can stop watching now because I'm not
going to cover anything else in this
tutorial.
We've covered this before, but if you want
revision because this
is a, a bit of a tricky topic then stay
tuned.
So I'm just going to right click the GUI
package, go to new interface and create an
interface here.
I'll call it, start panel listener.
Click finish.
And I'm going to give this one method,
public void start Game.
Like that.
And in my main class I'm gonna
say actually I'm thinking I'll leave that
for a minute because in the start panel,
I'm gonna edit this code by hand, so I'm
gonna give it a private,
private start panel listener, listener.
And let's just pass listeners to
constructor, so start, start panel in
fact, let's not do that
because I just thought maybe that would
give me
problems with my visual designer actually,
I'm not sure.
What I'll do is, I'll go down here, and as
I've done before many times in
these, in this series, I'll create public
void, set, listener.
And that takes start, start panel,
listener.
And if you wanted multiple things to
listen to the same panel, you would
just need to create an array of listeners
up here, instead of a single reference.
Like it could be just an array list.
And this method will be called add
listener and
it will just add your listener to that
array list.
Or you could have just separate variables
for different listeners.
It doesn't matter.
And I'll say, start.
Now, I call it listening type, so this,
whoops, where are we?
This.listener, equals listener so that
allows
me to set the listener, and then let's
just have a private void fire, start game.
And what that will do is it will say if
this listener
is not equal to null, then
listener.startgame.
Now finally, in my main, my main class
here, I can say, after
creating a start panel I can say
startpanel.add.set,
sorry, set listener I think I called it.
Set listener, new start panel listener.
And there we go.
Let's get rid of some of this extraneous
code, and add a
semicolon there, and in here just to prove
it works, so I'll do a sysout.
Hello there, and this is gonna start my
game.
But it's for this tutorial, I'm just gonna
leave it with this basically.
And then in this action performed here,
and the button, the action performed of
the
button on the start panel, I'm just gonna
call fire, start game, fire start game.
And fire start game just says okay, for
this is not null, call it start game
method.
And the listener that has been added,
listener's been added using set listener.
And, that's actually this anonymous class
here.
So it starts actually calling this method.
And if I run that, now, I click the
button, and there we go.
It says hello there, which is coming from
there.
So that's it for this tutorial.
Have fun with the visual designer.
And join me again next time.
And until next time, happy coding.