Hello this is John from
caveofprogamming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
card layout.
So, card layout let's you switch
between completely different views in your
application.
So if I run this now, I've got this panel
showing
up with a button that just outputs text at
the moment.
But I want this button to switch to a
completely different view.
Which is gonna be my game thingamajig.
And you can use card, a kind of card
layout.
It's like a kind of deck of cards
where you can switch between the different
cards.
And you can have as man as you like.
And I'm gonna use that to switch from this
to my game.
You can use them of course not only in
games but also
in, for example dialogue to create wizards
and all that kind of thing.
Now so here my main my main class
which is an applet in this particular
case.
I've got my two panels, so this is my game
is a J component it take up the whole
screen.
And this start panel is a panel, which of
course is also a type of jcomponent.
I'm gonna start here by creating here a
private card layout, card layout.
I'll call it cards and add the import with
Ctrl+Shift+O.
And in my init method, all this will be
your
probably your constructor if you're doing
a desktop screen program.
I'm gonna say Cards equals newCardLayout.
There we go.
And now where do I set layout, at the
moment I'm setting a board layout.
I am gonna change that to my card layout.
And when I do add, instead of adding using
these
board layout constants, I am gonna add
using a descriptive string.
So, I am gonna call the start panel, start
and then let's also add the game.
And I'll call that game.
So these are just strings that you kinda
make up so
you can refer to your different components
or panels later on.
And now, so if I run that the, the one
that I added first will be the
one that's visible, which is my start
panel,
so it still looks the same at the moment.
But what I'm gonna do is instead of
outputting hello
there when I click the button, I want to
say cards.show.
And show has two arguments here.
So let's try to bring up the autocomplete
for that cuz that will be informative.
cards.show.
There we go.
So you need to pass in the parent
container and and the
name that you added, the string that you
added when you did add.
Now if you yeah.
Actually, one thing I forgot to mention
before was that,
and this is the same for an applet or a
JFrame.
When you add components to the JFrame or
to a
JApplet with add you're not strictly
speaking, adding them to the
JFrame or JApplet class you're adding them
to its content
pane, which is kind of like a panel that
it contains.
And you can get that content pain if you
want.
I didn't get content pain.
And that will allow you to set it's
background color and all that kind of
thing.
So if you want to set the background color
of
JFrame you need to do,
getContentPane().setBackground or whatever
it is.
That's worth bearing in mind.
And the relevance here is that I don't
want
to pass in, literally a reference to the
parent.
I want to pass in a reference to the
content pane of the parent.
Now in an anonymous class here.
So if I type, I can't type this
getContactPanel because this would be
refer to this anonymous class here which
implements startPanelListener.
To get that this reference of the parent
frame, cuz my parent class is called main,
I can say main.this, which is kind of a
strange syntax but that's how it works.
And then, from there I can get the, I can
use, I can call up the getContentPane
method of the parent, in this case a
JApplet, or it may be a JFrame.
So let's add that in and so that gives me
the parent container of the, that
I've set the card layer on, which is
actually the content frame of this
enclosing main class.
And now I'm just gonna pass in the
descriptive string which is gonna be
game, because I want it to switch to game
when you click the button.
So now let's run that.
And of course, you can have as many of
these panels as you want, and switch
between different ones.
And in, yeah, I, I just wanna remind you
as well, in the last tutorial I added
to the content, the start panel here,
which I created using the visual designer.
I added this set listener method.
And I set the main class as a listener.
And I call fire start game, which calls
start game in the listener.
Actually, it's not the main class for
editors,
the list is strictly speaking, but this
anonymous class.
So when you click the button, invokes this
basically.
This is listening to the panel.
So let's just run that, and now if I click
new simulation, it
goes to my simulation or game or whatever
you like to call it.
So, that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at making this that actually work.
So, join me again then and until next
time, happy coding.