Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this tutorial
we're gonna look at handling intersections
between shapes.
So we're gonna look at how you can find
out if two shapes intersect.
Now in this case I've got here, I've got
an ellipse
2D, which I've called ball, and around it
rectangle 2D, which I've
called bat, and I wanna check if those two
things intersect,
because I wanna be able to hit my ball
with my bat.
So if I run this, at the moment it looks
like this.
Now shapes have a whole load of useful
methods here, and I'm gonna
go to my this game component I've created
has an update method where
it checks like every 20 milliseconds or
something if my ball has gone
off the edge of the screen and reverses
it's direction if it has.
So, in this update method I'm gonna add a
lets maximize the editor here, I'm gonna
add if or.intersect.
In fact I just want to show you this
whole bunch of useful methods on these
shapes, including contains.
So like for example if you get a point
back from your
mouse you can say does, is that point
contained by some shape.
And you can find out if someone's clicked
on a particular shape for example.
So there's a bunch of really useful
methods, and I'm going to use this
intersects, intersects methods, method
which checks if
this shape intersects a rectangle 2D
shape.
Now, I'm not using for my bar to
rectangle two, rectangle 2D, I'm using a
rounded rectan-,
rectangle 2D or is it called round
rectangle?
Yeah, it's called RoundRectangle 2D.
So I'm gonna, what I'm gonna do is, I'll
say ball.insects bat.get
bounds 2D, which returns a rectangle 2D,
that bounds the kind of rounded shape.
And I'm gonna say that if the ball
intersects that.
Now what I want to do is I wanna reverse
the direction of the ball if it intersects
the bat.
So I wanna say, like got its next
direction ball and I wanna say.
And that's gonna be equal to, that's
either equal to minus 1 or plus 1.
So I wanna equals x direction ball and
just put a negative sign in front of that.
And do the same for the y direction to
kind of give
an illusion at least of the ball bouncing
off the bat.
But now if if I do it like this, there's
a,
there's a risk that the ball could get
stuck on the bat.
'Cuz it will reverse the direction.
'Cuz it's found that the ball is
intersecting the bat.
But then, it's the next update, 20
milliseconds later, it
will say, okay it's still intersecting
potentially, reverse the direction again.
And the ball got stuck there.
So to take care of that I'm gonna add a
private instance variable up here.
Private boolean check, enter,
enterSection,
and let's set that initially to true.
And then I'm gonna say okay if if check
intersection, so if the
ball intersects the bat, and if checked
intersection, then I do all that stuff.
I reverse the direction of the ball.
And once the direction of the ball has
been reversed I'm gonna say, okay, don't
check it anymore, say check intersection
equals, whoops, equals false.
And then, check intersection is not gonna
be set to true until it's
not longer until the ball and bat are no
longer intersecting, so.
And this L which means that this board
does not
intersect the bar I'm gonna say check
intersection equals true.
So it only checks when it's found that the
ball
is clear of the bat and then it will check
once,
reverse the direction of the ball, and
then say, okay, don't
check it any more until it's clear of the
bat again.
Now lets run that, and with a bit of luck
I can now bounce the ball off the bat.
Let's see this is very difficult and there
we go, there we go, very nice.
Okay, so have fun with that and that's the
last tutorial in this series.
But if you would like to know, if there's
some topic that I haven't covered
that you would like to know more about,
feel free to send me a message.
I can't make any promises, but I may well
add an appendix that covers a few more
topics.
So that's it for this, and enjoy your new
found Swing programming skills.
Thank you very much for watching my
course.
You can find other stuff by me much of it
for
free, on YouTube and on
caveopprogramming.com, which is all one
word.
My name's John and as I say at the end of
every tutorial, happy coding.