Hello this is John from cave of programming.
A second video that I'm adding to this course.
Two years later after finishing the course.
So here I've got my running applet and I have applied the two fixes that I mention in the video that
I added at the start of this section of the course.
So the ball's bouncing the right way and it also works on the Mac.
And in this tutorial I'm going to show you how to get this working as a desktop app.
So this is pretty good.
Little challenge.
If you've been following along the tutorial and writing code itself and getting it to work then hopefully
you should be able to figure out how to create a desk top up from this.
In case you can't or in case you want to see an example of how you would actually do that.
I'm going to show you how to do it here.
So let's let's quit this and go to eclipse.
And the first thing I'm going to do here is we're going to need a we're going to need a J frame or a
class that extends Jay frame.
So I'm just going to add this to the existing code that includes the applet stuff and then we'll be
able to run it either as an app player or as a desktop program.
So I'm going to go to I'm going to right click and go to new class and let's call this mainframe and
click finish.
And I'm going to say that this extends Jay frame and I'm going to add Firstly the input at the top with
control shift so or command shift on the mark.
And we're going to call.
We're going to create a constructor here so mainframe like this I now call the version of the parent
class constructor that takes a string parameter.
That's just the title that goes on the window.
Let's call this animation demo.
So this error a lot of people have asked me about this and this this is just.
You may know it's just that if you extend the class that is serialise hippel or you make your class
in implement the serialise will interface.
Then you get this warning because this is just a thing so that if one save your objects to a file you
can have a version IDM which you can change if you create a new version of your program and you don't
want people loading the new version of your object from a file containing the old version.
So I cover serialisation in my job for beginners.
But for here I'm just going to add a generated serial version to I.D. just to get rid of that warnings
just it's just nice not to see it really they don't really always have to worry about these warnings
too much.
K. So in the constructor let's get this a size let's make make this call set size and set that to eight
hundred wide six hundred high.
I'm going to set it to visible and say set visible true to actually show the window.
And I'm also going to say set default close operation.
Unless this is just going to make it close.
When we click the cross in a corner of the window window exit on close is a constant from a frame.
We don't have to say J framed likes it on clothes because were already within a frame subclass here.
So that's that's just a really basic blank window.
Now let's go to the project right click and go to new class and I'll create a class with a main method.
I'll call this main notes call at map.
We've already got the main and ticked to say do you want the public static void main method.
And in there I need to call swing utilities dot invoke later invoke later.
So very people have asked me why we need to start this swink up this way why comany just go out and
create the J frame.
The best answer I can give is just that this is the recommended way of doing it.
Maybe it causes problems if you got multithreaded that if you don't do this or something like that but
this is the way Oracle recommends So it is the way we should do it.
This creates some kind of special thread that your swing runs in.
Now here we could say new runnable run ball like this add in brackets this is an anonymous class.
If I click the error I can go to add on implementing methods and in here we can add our j frame we can
create a frame just by saying new main frame.
That's the way I've been showing you how to do it in these videos.
But now if you're using Java 8 you can also use landell expressions instead and as.
I know in my free.
Dollar for beginners course.
Let's check the list works.
First going to right click up Doc chaffer and go to run as job application.
And now we get a blank window here.
So an alternative way an alternative to Anonymous classes like this.
If you've got an anonymous class just to implement an Interface only has one method called functional
interfaces in Java.
A terminology you can do with a land expression and that little like this will have two round brackets
and an arrow like that.
And then a couple of brackets where we can put in some code and then we can just do the same thing say
new J frame.
So this is just the equivalent syntax to all we have before rarely with the anonymous class.
Sign new mainframe.
It's just a bit more terse and this is called.
This is a just a simple example of what we call a land expression.
It just great allows you to create little anonymous functions that you can pass to other functions to
other methods.
And you can also use these in the same way for handling button clicks which is quite nice.
That's just a few using Java a.
So let's check it again.
It's run as Java application and yet looks like it's working.
So now we can just copy some code into our mainframe.
So normally I would try to avoid copying code but here we have you know we've clearly got a some Aplin
related code here and we just need this in our alternative Jay frame swing related desktop code.
So here I am just going to copy this.
Probably you wouldn't want the applet code and the swing code in the same Java application but there's
no harm in leaving this in here.
You'll still be able to run it as a desktop.
So I'm just going to copy all this stuff at the top of the J applet in main Java code.
I'm going to copy all these variables over to mainframe.
Let's paste them in here and we'll go back to the main Java the uplook code and copy all this stuff
from init.
We need all of that.
Go back to mainframe Java and I'm going to put that in the constructor before we make the window visible.
Still looks like we have to do a little bit of work here and slits to save that actually and see what
it says.
So now we need to get in this anonymous class here.
We could use the lander expression for that.
I think this only has one interface.
Sorry one method this interface but I'll leave it as it is.
Let's just open that because yes so here we could use alandra expression we got an interface which is
one method.
But equally there's no harm leaving it like this.
What we do need to change is now mainframe's of this not maned on this to get there.
This reference of the mainframe and here where were creating a timer.
I think this year the only thing we have to do here is our class here is going to have to implement
action listener let's say imply men's action listener so that we can create a method that is called
by the timer.
It's clear the error the warning.
Yeah it's an error actually go to import action listner click it again and go to add on implementing
methods.
And now we get this which is going to be called every time the timer runs.
So go back to maned Java and we can see that previously we called game of date and the action performed
for our timer.
So now we need to do the same thing just pace that in here.
The other thing is we need to start a timer.
In the original uplook code we've got this code that calls time indot star when the applets is started
and calls time indot Stop when the apla Stops when it goes into the background or whatever.
That's not really relevant with swingarm.
We just want to start running and carry on running.
Really.
Probably.
So let's go to make framed Java and somewhere in here.
Sure we show the window.
It doesn't really matter actually we'll call time it does start now free right click here and go to
run as Java application instead of our plr.
Hopefully will see the same thing.
So here it is.
Now its running as a desktop.
We clicked this and it works just as before.
Okay so the you can apply these animation techniques to swing desktop that's just like this and that
is most often where you're probably gonna want to use them especially since it kind of looks like applets
might be on their way out.
To be honest with Chrome not supporting them but people I'm sure are still going to be using it for
some time.
I'm just within companies where as I say as I said in the video at the start of the course you can control
what browser people uses you use and you can control the security settings of the browser.
Okay so that's it for this tutorial.
Until next time.
Happy coding.